all right hey everyone it's active infer
an stream number
7.1 and it should be a great and
exciting stream it's November 7th
2024 711 depending on where you are and
I'm going to begin the stream with a
GitHub push that we are going to spend
the next several hours probably
unpacking let's commit it push it and
begin what will be a very fun
exploration into the active inference
institute's branch of Pi
mdp while it's writing let's jump into
the show here's where we're heading
we're heading into shly value analyzed
homeostatic satisfaction expected free
energy belief accuracy and control
efficiency
analyses for multiple differently
parameterized pmdp agents base risk
averse exploratory and balanced on those
measures being able to analyze
combinatorics like the synergies of
their belief accuracy control efficiency
expected free energy and homeostatic
satisfaction we can look at the report
and explore different topics like with
respect to those variables what's the
mean shapley contribution Coalition
performance best coalitions this is all
combinations of 0 1 2 3 and four so for
example for expected free energy we see
that the four unit Coalition is the best
whereas for homeostatic
satisficing zero Agent Zero working
alone does the
best underneath these coalitions and
their combinatorics are specific agents
that are logged in individual
experiments and here's some of the plots
and how that looks for each IND
individual agent this is a given active
inference agent here we have policy
entropy over time action selection
distribution belief observation
cycle belief accuracies over time
homeostatic State distributions and
trajectories state
transitions policy selection probability
policy updating decrease maintain and
increase belief Dynamics third time
hidden State
beliefs action frequencies policy
convergences belief
convergences correlations between
beliefs and actions and action
confidences so what that Chaple analysis
is doing is running all the
combinatorics under the hood this is
going to be a wild ride so let's confirm
that the GitHub has pushed I'll put the
code Link in welcome to the7
fork in the live chat I will look
forward to everyone's comments I am
going
to ensure that we
are pushing the right
way it still has not
loaded let's begin
though with
a007
here taking a little bit of time to
upload on GitHub okay here we go little
bit more context before we dive into
what may be some absurdly technical but
really useful and interesting things
that have happened over the last few
days and
hours here's the
stream GNN for agent maker for pmdp for
active bio firms for Biore regionalism
for ants let's decompress that title
generalized notation notation GNN as
semantic middleware for agent maker a
custom robust modular agent engineering
framework using pmdp Python language
package for marov decision processes
with methods for active inference and
free energy based inference methods for
biof firms as proposed by John
clippinger as a paradigm for firms in
the age of Biore regionalism as a mode
of Life Co extensis for species like
ants people and
Beyond here's some live stream Cod names
and an only lightly redacted preludium
for your priors only predictions are not
enough the agent who minimized Me On Her
Majesty's statistical service Quantum of
precision
live and Le update Professor friston do
you expect me to reach the Optima no I
expect you to
optimize just like they wrote at the end
of the 2022 textbook when the last words
were ultimately we are confident that
you will continue to pursue active
inference in some
form is that agents generative model in
mdp yes an mdp a PO
mdp as if the media were not already the
message for you this is a just in time
live stream going through raw open
source code I know that there are
bugs as well as typos incorrect or
ineffective calculations other errors
this is speculative realism embodied in
chaotic large scale code coordination
using cursor
0.424 and Claude 3.5 Sonet 2024 1022 use
these linguis IC and computational
symbols at your own risk and
Delight if and as you are so inclined
you are invited to join our adventure
and journey partially disclosed here in
now let's check again in the GitHub and
proceed on
regardless I'm on another Fork
that's what happens when you're on wild
roads it will come to the institute's
repo it went to my own personal accounts
let's head over
there I'm putting in the YouTube live
chat my own
doxology GitHub and we're going to
continue on through there
pmdp agent
maker stream
007 all
right little bit of background
information before we jump into the code
thanks those who are in the live chat
write any comments and questions and you
may get memd on
stream we are working on robust
middleware that interfaces between core
active inference implementations and
Powerful accessible interpretable
semantic toolkits for synthetic
intelligence
engineering architecture
layers here's a way to think about
active inference middleware and active
inference as middleware as we will
reveal later on layer one core or kernel
inference implementations today we're
going to be looking at that with PDP in
the Python programming language we can
also make this happen through
generalized notation notation using RX
and fur. JL Julia
we could use machine learning
methods also known as amortized
inference in different languages at the
core we could use logical reasoning like
JF cler's symbolic active inference work
we could at the core use biological soft
active and Quantum matter and other
substrates what we're focusing on here
is the middleware layer specifically
we're going to be peeling back to the
point where we look at NN as an
interface between the inner and the Miso
layers middleware for active
inference pending future reer
understandings is packages like agent
maker which we're going to look at today
farmworks infra ants and other kinds of
domain or domain General systems that
interface between the core
implementation methods which as part of
their beauty and elegance have
Simplicity and outer layer systems of
Interest real world touch points and
design interfaces and domain adaptations
mapping to meso or outer layers so think
about Farm OS as running on a farm
embodiment core and
facing farmers and individuals
interacting with that data set to give
an agricultural example something
similar is happening for active
inference here's another key analogy g&n
plus agent maker plus PDP plus Etc plus
Plus+ is to active inference as
ebpf is to the Linux kernel the slogan
of evf and check it out if you haven't
looked into it already is dynamically
program the kernel for efficient
networking observability tracing and
security we can modify that slogan for
GNN agent
maker dynamically program the agent for
robust and efficient inference planning
and
action okay here's the an analysis
agenda we're going to run biofirm dopy
and all it entails running back layers
layers layers layers layers we're going
to talk about eventually getting back to
the root of the generation and the
initialization initiation of the
agent in the generalized notation
notation format and then we will Trace
back that
to an April 2023 paper written with the
now Stanford graduate student
yakup it was a great collaboration last
year and we made many mimetic thrusts
and queries towards developing this into
something that could be used with llms
we put it on the shelf for a little bit
for a few months and now GNN is back not
with a Vengeance but with a functional
utility that surprised even
me after running through the script in
its functional and analytical Beauty we
will return to first whatever ideas
people have added in the live chat talk
about open source
development testing deployment education
security Theory math art and more and
about what comes after agent
maker1 I'd also like to recognize some
of the recent events and developments in
the biofirm repo following INF for ant
stream six oh how long ago by Andrew
Pasa who has added some very cool
surprise and shly value modeling let's
take a look at
that here's the history of surprise for
these different natural resource biofirm
sub
agents
and their token
accumulation history in a shapley value
oriented incentive Paradigm super cool
Andrew it pushed me over the edge to add
in the shly value before this stream and
I'm super looking forward to the
collaborations and where this all goes
I'd also like to show a cursor
acknowledgement this is in the midst of
some truly heated epistemic moments that
Claude 3.5 son it 2024 1022 and I shared
I wrote this is incredible work FYI
everyone thanks you just give the
acknowledgement he that you feel proper
then we will continue with the
work Claude wrote thank you for the kind
words I should acknowledge that this
work Builds on several important
foundations active inference Theory PDP
framework homeostatic control and
software engineering shall we continue
with the work yes Claude
let's okay we are in the agent maker
folder within the
pmdp package
itself following the biofirm
006 Stream
as usual it was getting messy and choppy
with all of these scripts calling each
other from the same folder we were
getting a little bit complex for our
britches and it was time to think about
not just calling the core PDP utilities
but burrowing in making stigmergic
tunnels among them and being a part of
the pmdp package which again I hope to
and we will push and develop on The
Institute Branch for the stewardship
that that can
afford biofirm again Standalone calling
PDP but what we'll be looking at for the
rest of the stream is burrowed in amidst
the pmdp
modules are several new modules that
have been added so let's do a side by
side with the
pmdp and
the pmdp
fork so here we
are with the
fork
sidebar and here we are with the main
sidebar so in the main package the
folders under PDP are alos which are
algorithms environments
and Jax which is like a sub Branch for a
lot of methods that uses the python Jax
method there's been a proliferation of
folders I really have to say agent maker
alphabetically is first we're going to
look more at agent maker a lot following
agent maker alos remains Mes in remains
we have the GNN folder which we're going
to get to in part two
we have the maths folder some of this is
just arbitrary others is
accidental there's the meta pmdp folder
with but one simple script which outputs
a plain text folder concatenating all
the PDP methods in a text
file reflects with ad Json and a text
file the folder structure of the meta
repo this is another useful trick that
you can use in other repos it helps give
extra context an extra helping of
context we might even say to cursor so
that it can do the accurate cross folder
operations we need there's a utils
folder there are also PDP util scripts
but I wanted to make a separate folder
to keep them separate inv versionable
and then there's a visualization folder
with a variety of biofirm GNN and Matrix
visualization methods so
let us go to now the agent Mak maker
folder and we're going to start from the
outermost layer which is trying to
understand the shoply value
contributions to the homeostasis of
different combinations of multi-agent
systems and this has been absolutely
championed by John clippinger so for
this and many of other contributions
made by John and other people it's just
awesome that we can see active inference
getting to a point where we can actually
run out these incredible shoply analyses
that themselves are built upon multiple
levels of inference and
intelligence okay first to the biofirm
shapley script that was run 1,200 lines
again as another discourse that I will
try not to return to that much cursor
plus improvements in llms has been
completely transformative check the
earlier infan streams from who knows how
many days ago even at 3 400 lines of
code we were splitting them now on top
of a functional run biofirm script it
can pop out with a few prompts 1,200
functional lines that take the
operativity of one functional biofirm
agent and wrap that into another
incredible layer so right click open an
integrated terminal Python 3 biofirm
shapley Let's analyze what is happening
when we run
this it begins with creating in this
case because it's looking at multiple
different agents it creates multiple
agent variations on a theme kind of like
Geral
lerach and defines the metrics and
defines the combinatorics of the agent
coalitions 0 1 2 3 4 agents A tet's all
you need
it then enters into the experimentation
at the level of each
Coalition defines the output directory
the environment the agent now we're
popping down into the level of this
first biofirm
experiment stage one Matrix rendering
here the environment and agent GNN are
brought in and logged copiously again
ebpf the logging how many times have we
all been coding with pmdp and then it's
like shape 3 comma 0 can't be coerced
into a numpy array and it's like what so
that is a lot of the abstraction that I
sought to abstract over here okay it it
happened a little bit fast and pushed us
away where we were I'm just going to run
it again so that
we
okay just so we can see stage 1 two 3
for given
experiment so here's another
experiment Coalition 1 Z output
environment agent stage one Matrix
rendering initializing the biofirm
renderer loging copiously all the
combinatorics of where everything is
going to it's not for me it's for the
llm
we get into the loading of the GNN
models there's normalization methods
that happened I did ask I said are you
really sure like it's giving me a
warning about action zero and two not
being normalized and it's like relax
you're just not being wide enough with
how you're accepting it being normalized
or not I thought okay fine it works it
works but like many things these can be
improved it loads in and describes the
shape of all the variable s that are
needed and this was the big work that
yakup and I engaged in which was surely
we can have some kind of markdown syntax
or dialect that would enable the triple
play a pragmatic approach to expressing
GNN in linguistic Visual and executable
and graphical cognitive models yes there
are four components in the triple play
and how would we have that kind of
Integrity across
representations that's what GNN enables
and and we're going to peel back to that
layer after defining the matrices and
their
shapes the actual simulation begins to
occur and there's some logging giving
peeping into the actions that are being
taken the values and so on matrices are
saved and
validated along the
way environment matrices and agent
matrices are saved that was the first
phase in the
simulation the the time steps that are
specified in the config
file are
used so here is a
very builtup config file
defining project route paths environment
and the meaning and we're going to
return to this GNN has the absolutely
critical role of separating the state
space
specification the
parameterization of a variable with the
English language active inference
ontology assertion about that variable
without that kind of an articulation
you'll end up naming your variables
thing like observation and that makes
sense when you're just thinking about
one agent but that agent's observation
goes on to become someone else's action
or vice versa so how do we prevent using
natural
language to implicitly semantically load
the names of this the
variables how do we move to a place
where we can make uniquely identifiable
computationally tagged variables and
then have one or more assertions about
what to call those variables so GNN is
all about having a little bit of a gap
and space between the specification of
the variable and how we think about its
role in the active inference onology
here's the experimental config name of
the experiment time steps rendering
options to render visualize cleaning
output here are the parameters that are
getting past so this is well set up for
those who like to sweep across
parameters like ecological noise
that's how much the ecosystem varies on
its own controllability that's the
efficacy of action of the agent whether
it knows it or not policy Precision this
is how the policy posterior sharpened
from the policy prior by expected free
energy is modulated by then a
temperature term that either sharpens or
flattens distinctions amongst policy
posteriors use State info gain is true
that is using epistemic value in policy
selection as an Information Gain term as
opposed to flagging this to false would
only calculate expected utility and
functionally be like a reward or
reinforcement or utility maximizer
inference Horizon has been kept at one
I'm not sure how planning would unfold
but it'd be possible it work or we'd
have to see and then action selection
could be stochastic sampling from the
policy posterior or deterministically
drawing the most upweighted
policy and then some Flags related to
the tracing and logging within the
active inference Loop which is giving us
a new visibility into what's happening
at each time step for each agent in this
setting simulation is executed goes
through the time steps and then in stage
three which is where we interrupted it
it does agent specific everything right
now is being output into this
sandbox fold
subfolder biofirm so each experiment
let's look through what
happens okay first render now this is
all reflecting what run biofirm does run
biofirm is a small scripts of only less
than 300
lines and what it does is it logs and
times as we'll see now Python 3 run
biofirm
now we're going to see what the shapley
experiment was doing across coalitions
of multiple agents and we're just going
to run that for one agent for one Trace
so let's let's clear it and run it
deleting sandbox and looking at how the
outputs are made run
bioferm okay we see it start up first
thing is we see sandbox come on folders
are made where they're not and so this
process of iteratively deleting the
folders rerunning deleting rerunning
deleting rerunning going to a different
machine seeing if it works without
installing and all this other stuff
that's part of making this at least some
extent robust but of course I'm looking
forward to working with more experienced
and software Engineers who can really
work with some of these raw Concepts and
make them do something that this is only
hinting at so here we go full trace for
one agent maker run
biofirm event let's call it so biofirm
experiment is called bioform experiment
output directory environment and agent
files as GNN files let's take a quick
peek at what the agent GNN files look
like here we see the agent defined in
terms of the state space that it's
operating in that's the ecological State
that's the latent State that's like
temperature in the room here there's
three discrete options and we're going
to give them a label so so again this
opens up the idea of having like English
labels and then we could have another
field for a different
language because it puts some space
between the name and what it's really
doing functionally here's similar for
observation and also within the
observation is the a metrix associated
with that
modality another thing I'll mention is I
began with testing the GNN concept on
the T am example from pmdp and I
overbuilt a
multimodality GNN situation for the
multimodality teamas and then pulled it
back to the single modality biofirm
again just another method for
overbuilding and then pruning back to
functionality here's the the a matrix
specified it next to the observations
Associated a matrix with the observation
here's the transition model this is the
B Matrix with respect to ecological
State the matrices are defined here so
for those who are learning what the
syntax and semantics of active inference
AB bcde e are this hopefully can make it
really clear instead of being specified
like in a browser accessible notebook it
gives a first introductory place to look
at how the matrices work however for
modulating and mutating and genetic
algorithms and sweeping and optimization
all these things this kind of Machinery
is what yakob and I have been thrilled
about for years now policies Pi all the
information that's required for PDP to
handle the specification of these
policies and the GNN can be overbuilt
you could have policies like whether it
is acceptable like can7 do it or
only1 and then if a given rendering
didn't need to know that information it
could just discard from the Json or not
take it into account preferences that's
the C Matrix here it's a preference over
the obser the State observation the
observations and the C Matrix looks like
04 0 with the associated labels low
homeostatic and high so again the
separation between the variables used in
active inference for the shapes and
sizes they are and the English language
assertions of annotations with active
inference on toy terms is a gap that if
you can keep it open will give you so
many more abilities to work with active
inference in different settings and then
lastly the initial beliefs or the D
Matrix the initial prior on ecological
State linked through the keys of that
name and it's 80% in homeostatic and 10%
for each of low and high so that's an
example of what the biofirm GNN looks
like like and then here's the biofirm
environments this is a slightly simpler
GNN file here it again hinges on the
same ecological State that's how we can
connect hidden State factors as an agent
infers them to be and the actual
ecological simulation happening in the
generative process or in the surrounding
environment otherwise you can have a
situation where it's like okay the
agent's predicting temperature and then
the ecological simulation is pH
and then how would we even know when
we're going to be working in settings
with so many different variables and
observations and latent States and more
and Plus+ plus that the idea of loading
the semantics of what something does
into the English language of a variable
name quickly you will understand why
yakup and I did what we did here we have
the observations being passed from the
environment that's like an a matrix for
the environment
it has an symmetric a
matrix here's the transition model of
the environment so check out chapter 7
in the 22 textbook or step by-step by
Smith at all where there's a step up
from static basy and perception
to Dynamic basian perception the music
listening example where there's
probabilistic inference about what no is
supposed to be played based upon what no
is heard but there's no action
intervention in between the hidden State
updates so it's like a single slice of B
that's just a partially observable
Markov process but not a decision
process and then here to actually make
it an
mdp the agent actions are given the
efficacy represented in these from to
matrices as slices of B so there's
different ways that you could simulate
the environment it could just be like
a government API or it could be a PDP or
it could be a p MP or it could be a
MP and then the initial state in terms
of sampling from a prior on its own sort
of D so that's what the GNN file looks
like but we're going to pull back to
some of the other methods that are
needed to make the GNN happen okay back
to the
running the matrices are rendered
I'm going to run another experiment just
to show what it looks like in the
sandbox hello Andrew hello Benji hello
XZ
qz
zy so now in
sandbox it takes a little bit for the
sidebar to catch up with What's
Happening Here in sandbox biofirm now
there's two experiments one that was
modified at 459 one at
506 let's just
do a
brief
pmdp
push just for the stapling and the
temporal
weaving
okay let's reopen sandbox here are the
two experiments now in the sandbox with
their time
steps getting back to what each of these
three steps do so render is the first
stage within each of the experiments
render is a folder output by biofirm
render here we're looking at a 730 line
script calling many other methods and
this was the entry point I said first
let's get to reading in a GNN file and
rendering what we're about to see
here we
have
first replicating for cursor's context
and for reproducibility the exact Json
of the agent environment simulation
parameters and validation compliance
report for the
validations that's in the config under
one render two logs I guess the logs go
to the outer folder that's just copying
what is a summary of what happened to
the terminal like it it it perhaps could
be put under here with other
logs here are the matrices as numpy
arrays ABC and D for the agent and a b
and d cuz the environment is not modeled
here with preferences so again this is
showing the the tiniest hint of the
flexibility of GNN which is like well
the agent class in
pmdp expects certain variables but what
if we wanted to have an agent with a
very different architecture or a
dynamical
architecture then we'd want to have
these gnns that could be arbitrarily
composed # category Theory and then have
those matrices in formats that are going
to be easy to read in and read out
earlier versions had them also coming as
text and other files and things like
that so it could be visualized but
they're shown visually in the GNN file
if you want to check so this helps
semantically interface so that the next
level of analysis in the next phase two
in the simulation it can just say okay
where are my a b c and d at it doesn't
need to know that b is related to this
and has that
name that's output for the agent in the
environment in the matrices folder and
then there's the Matrix
visualizations so here again for those
who are aren't we all learning and
applying active inference we see the a
matrix of the agent so this is the
ambiguity Matrix or the mapping between
hidden States and observations so if
this were all ones as an identity Matrix
it'd be a noisess situation and that's
the difference between a PDP and an mdp
PDP means partially observable which
means we do have a nonidentity a matrix
which means we do have some kind of
partial observability or ambiguity
between observations and the latent
states that they're associated with we
have the slices of the B Matrix these
are the three actions the agent can take
here they're not sharply tuned to too
much but just to to generally represent
that if our current state this is Agent
agent transition model for actions 0 1
and two which are decrease maintain and
increase so here let's just look at
maintain first action number one which
is the second indexed action here you
can see there's some
off values however most of the values
are on the diagonal so this is like
saying if you choose to maintain and
you're in low 90% of the time you're
going to be in low 10 10% of the time
you're expecting to transition to
homeostatic if you're in homeostatic and
you maintain that's what slice were on
then you're going to 80% of the time
remain homeostatic 10% of the time
you're going to move to higher low and
analogously with maintain and high now
here's action increase and decrease and
so these ones you can see with the 83
and the 62 are reflections of each other
like reflections of each other and this
is saying let's just look at for
increase here when our current state is
low and conditioned upon us going high
there's an 83% chance of staying low and
a 177% chance of going to
homeostatic so compare just those
8370 to 910 0 so this is
reflecting or encoding the belief about
differential action efficacy
that there's a 10% chance of leaving low
if I maintain and there's a 177% chance
of transitioning out of low to medium if
I increase and you can follow through
all of these and that's part of the fun
of learning active inference the C
Matrix here's a preference 0 4 0 this is
going to come into play for the
pragmatic value or utility calculations
in the expected free energy based policy
inference and here's d d
the initial prior on latent States 80%
that it's in homeostatic 10% on high or
low then we have the same matrices for
the environment a slices of B and then D
no C Matrix for the reasons that we
discussed okay so that's the first
script one
render again run biofirm is going to run
render then
execute then visualize so now on to
stage two simulation this one was a lot
of fun to work through there's a lot of
Json configuration files the simulation
is deeply
tracked and I think you know what I mean
and then step three is the analysis
here's the anal the summary time series
so this Stacks up all the time series
that were made in the subfolders and
then here's the summarization this is
kind of the statistical
analysis could be like for a paper or
something and the summary time series so
here we see all those different kinds of
unfolding patterns through time in this
case it's 1,000 time steps so again we
see the relationship between the
environmental State and
observations so that is mostly aligned
because of the 90% accuracy relationship
between the environmental State and OB
obervation here's belief
Dynamics so we can see low homeostatic
and high blue orange and green so it
switches its beliefs about what state
it's in several times here's action
selection there's only three
actions here's policy probabilities so
it's kind of interesting that you can
see some relationships here and again
the matrices here were not intended to
be performant I didn't sweep over which
matrices to use it was just to show that
these kinds of methods can be
effectively
implemented system entropy in terms of
the belief and the policy
entropy and the belief accuracy could be
looked at like with a 50 step moving
average in terms of how accurate are
these beliefs and extra logs so that's
one agent for one homeostatic biofirm
modality for a thousand times
and then again what the shoply value
experiment
does Python 3 same
folder
biofirm
chapley what that's going to do is it's
going to run through all these
coalitions and do this single agent
analysis on the combinations of
coalitions I didn't look at too much of
the detail of how those coalitions are
actually like coordinated together but
again it's just a starting point so
let's pull back to the agent maker
overall stream and then we can look
into several of these
scripts
okay let's look a little bit at the read
me
for this
folder okay so here's the concept of
biofirm
GNN we have concept of biofirm read me
for the biofirm and read me for the
biofirm chapley so let's start with the
concept of the biofirm GNN I'm going to
paste this link directly in the live
chat a production framework for active
inference in complex systems the biof
from GNN framework provides an
Enterprise grade
oh that's two kind implementation of
active inference for complex adaptive
systems with particular emphasis on
homeostatic control in biological and
eological context this framework
addresses fundamental challenges in
deploying active inference at scale
through a modular production ready
architecture and we can look in the
terminal producing it is this isn't just
llm generated project planation this is
something I did over the last few days
technical innovation
this system introduces several key
Innovations in active inference
computation distributed Matrix
operations I wouldn't say that these are
even accurate so as with everything I'm
saying grains of salt please there is a
lot that is valid though and I do try to
prune out however when it's these
readmes long documents I'm not always
reviewing it for a more final and formal
performance version and document the
technical road map would not be Quantum
inspired belief propagation it would be
something more along the lines of what I
handw wrote which is
like my preference is to do appropriate
relevant open-source contributions via
Institute scaffolded mechanisms I do not
and cannot understand the leverage
consequences of action and safest future
development of these open- Source active
inference projects if you are passionate
curious and interested please consider
donating to The Institute donate. active
inference
Institute and or join our teams we will
explore new modes of software
engineering development and deployment
and again in this interlude while we're
here a great conversation yesterday with
Vladimir bin fellow investigator and we
talked about another three- layer stack
at the beginning of the stream I talked
about this core kernel inference
implementation layer a middle wear layer
that connects GNN to to domains of
Interest like agents farms and ants and
then the outer layer of touch points and
with Vladimir we had an awesome time
talking about intelligent soft matter
and thinking about low road the high
road and the Miso so in this trialectic
the low road is like the bottom up or
minute particulars for example the focus
on the farm the actuality of the farm
whereas in in the earlier Triad the core
was the algorithms on the metal or
neurons or whatever but here the low
road is the bottomup focus from what are
we observing what are the agents what
are the informational resources what are
the actions what is
happening the misol layer is active
inference here with a bridging and
gapping rooll onto the high road which
is actually its own dialectic the twin
principles of free energy principle
which is the Bas and Mechanics for
informational physics and the principles
of pattern in potentiality of living
matter and that's how life and
matter finds potential through pattern
and pattern through potential so this is
another way to think about active
inference as a connection between
systems of interest in their minute
particulars and principles of
information geometry and information
physics like Fe and principles some we
know some we don't of the patterns and
potentialities of living
matter but
[Music]
returning to the readmes so that's the
concept just talking about here's how to
implement the biofirm and here's how it
could be pointing towards a production
framework for biofirm engineering here's
the read me for the biofirm it goes
through and it describes what this
biofirm active inference agent is
biofirm is an active inference agent
that maintains homeostasis in simple
ecological environment the agent uses
the generalized neural network notation
of course that is a
typo sometimes it does graph neural
network the agent uses the GNN notation
to Define its generative model and
operates in a discrete State space with
three states low homeostasis and high so
for those who are keeping score the box
score at home we have the environment
model that a
d
PDP and then there's the agent model
which is the ABCD
PDP there's no policy selection in the
environment model it accepts the
transition slice dictated by the
agent here's how you use biofirm you run
run biofirm dopy and as mentioned that
runs those three stages per experiment
render which looks over to the GNN
folder for the GNN input and it's it's
still going with the simulation so just
showing how many times even though it's
only 100 ACM time steps first runs
render then runs execute then runs
visualize here's the directory structure
including documents like this and meta
pmdp is so helpful for
cursor I think they've also improved on
their side the folder handling which
earlier on was kind of an issue it would
put things in folders where it wasn't
supposed to be but giving a gentle plain
text reinforcement and then going up to
that
gear and reindexing or deleting your
index and reindexing this can make sure
that really gets it what the folder
structure is here are the key
files here's the analysis outputs
configuration
outputs different dependencies you want
to learn more check the references
active inference Theory and
implementation GNN specification
document we can
add a link to that
and homeostatic control and allostatic
eventually control models in active
inference that's the Run GNN script now
let's look at the shly value this was a
late breaking
development again though it was only
several prompts on top of
run so that was very encouraging because
it suggests that higher
order engineering is going to be
exponentially facilitated by robust
middleware surprise surprise # open
source biofirm shly value analysis the
shly value analysis module biofirm shly
dopy provides a comprehensive framework
for evaluating agent contributions in
multi-agent biofirm systems this
analysis helps understand agent
synergies optimal combinations and
individual strengths using Cooperative
Game Theory principles so here are the
four agents we
have the base agents with a standard 040
homeostatic preference there is the risk
averse agents with a
060 C representing sharper pragmatic or
utility seeking Behavior hence risk
aversion three the exploratory agent
with a
0.12.1 c reflecting a lower preference
differential and then the quote balanced
agent I don't know in what sense it's
balanced of course specul speculative
speculative it has a
131 with a compromise between stability
and adaptation all this depends on
environmental properties and so on here
are the performance metrics while shappy
value has completed so we'll look over
the performance metrics and then revisit
the shapley outputs homeostatic
satisfaction it's calculated as the time
in homeostasis divided by the total
time expected free energy measures
predictive performance
the components are calculated as
ambiguity the informational elements of
epistemic value even though that's not
exactly the term that we might associate
with epistemic value the read me did and
a risk term or pragmatic value and that
is normalized to allow comparable
analyses belief accuracy that's the
state estimation Precision how accurate
are the inferences about latent States
and then the control efficiency and
there's a lot of control measures so
this is just taken as a sort of standin
for the kinds of sense making analyses
that we can do with cognitive modeling
and compute and these are the kinds of
control theoretic or
decisionmaking measures that we can make
forensically historically post Haw we
can do realtime now casting and
anticipatory control efficiency as Carl
recently said somewhere allostasis is
planning to be homeostatic
here's the analysis framework itself
here's the Coalition the Coalition is
defined as the agents the metrics and
the coalitions the coalitions are
defined in terms of in this situation
all the possible agent combinations so
we could run it with five agents and we
may do that soon performance evaluation
looks at those four performance
measures and then here's the shapley
calculation
I let it Let It Go whether it was an
accurate shly calculation or not so if
this isn't like the best or the only or
the right way to calculate it it's an
equation that can be modified again the
directory
organization visualization
Suite agent contributions Coalition
performance metric analysis Advanced
visualization and then here's some of
what it considers Advanced features
okay so now that the shle value has been
output it ran all these sub experiments
with the
coalitions here's the shoply again
so Chaple config here are those agents
so it did a base agent and again GNN so
exciting load in a base biofirm agent
then do agent variations again kind of
goach
Conure variations on a theme gerer boach
detecting a
theme modifying the base
agents with customize preference
distributions that's how we can sweep
across agents willy-nilly
more information on the
simulation logs here we have everything
that's output to the
terminal including shapely value
analysis so homeostatic coming in rank
one we have the risk averse agents with
a relative impact of
50.7% all numbers are for speculative
realism purposes don't act on them
specifically and a value of plus 02
whereas the base
agent with this stochastic stample of I
believe 100 time steps replicated
times we must announce that it was
0.0013 value thank you for playing Agent
rank four base expected free energy
again the relative impact and this
connects to Andrew's work showing how
the surprisal level and the epistemic
and the pragmatic elements of agent
contributions can be weighted and valued
in terms of their relative impact to
Coalition success and performance
here we have the top three coalitions in
terms of homeostatic satisfaction like
this is as fun as the
Olympics risk averse
alone with a. 34
performance base plus exploratory
interesting with a.
33 I expected that from them and then
the risk averse plus balance with a 32
the worst three coalitions let's not
mention them expected free energy we
have the base and the risk averse
seemingly with a higher better value so
it's
interesting it could just be a quirk of
the way that the matrices are set up
with a certain kind of
sloppy partially observable combinations
that's what we're going to use GNN to
sweep sweep sweep over how how do
homeostatic satisfaction meta coalitions
correlate with expect free energy sense
making accuracy and control efficacy
coalitions Synergy analysis this looks
at across cooccurrences of given agents
in
coalitions what is their Synergy I don't
even know what scale it's on but here
are some negative synergies we're not
going to mention those and here are some
positive synergies base and risk
averse have a strong Synergy together
then the visualizations are output we
get kind of report cards on these
different agents in terms of their
contribution to homeostasis minimizing
uncertainty accurate State estimation
and control efficiency like is this
Badges and metals for a new kind of
Officer
core and again we can revisit there's
the agents themselves I don't know if
there's anything in that
folder that one's empty
maybe intentionally so maybe maybe this
page was left blank here are
coalitions again are those empty they
are but the coalitions are described in
the in the configuration and in the
experiments themselves if it's being
done properly at all again though
looking at the
reporting at the very least something
wildly close is happening here's the
calculation of the shly values so we
have F subi of V is sum over the
absolute value of the combinatorics of
the Coalition leave one out for agent I
multiplied by this value over the number
of combinations combinatorial multiplied
by
that and we get interesting analyses
like antagonistic pairs synergistic
pairs so these are fun reports and when
we look at the plots again these were
briefly flashed in the beginning we can
see okay here are the coalitions let's
look at homeostatic
satisfaction here we have the one
four-way
combo 303 performance this could be
stochastic it's only run for 100 steps
here just so it doesn't take too too
long and then we see hm
within each there's a
ranking risk
averse by itself does the
best for
homeostasis but then risk
averse doesn't help
others in synergizing when there's a
team of two or three or
four that's one interesting pattern and
then we see that kind of reflect
did in a rotationally symmetric way take
this and rotate it
180° here we see RIS alone with the best
homeostasis and with the with the low
relatively but expected free energy for
those who will recall equation 2.6 in
the textbook from
2022 it's not just about homeostatic
satisfaction so then if we look at the
belief accuracy the sense making and the
control efficiency which isn't playing a
role in the homeostatic or the expected
free energy calculations but we see kind
of a
resemblance like hm
exploratory looks and and also the axes
need interpretability and all this but
again looking at the rotational symmetry
it's like okay RIS Bal bass exp rist
bass X Bal huh so these two are in a
different order but it
Rhymes Chaple analysis here we see the
agent
contributions so this is the
contributions to homeostatic
satisfaction so it's like Risk
averse is a positive contributor to
homeostatic satisfaction I knew you
would but then when we look back at risk
of
verse was it that
one and we see the contribution like huh
risk averse contributes to homeostatic
sat
satisfaction but it's a negative
contributor to belief accuracy it's like
well that that does make sense from an
active inference perspective more risk
averse so having a sharper temperature
preference will make you take more
Extreme Action to keep the temperature
of the body or the room in
homeostasis at the cost of less accurate
beliefs about the
world and we see an interesting pattern
with the balanced one again it's not
balanced in any real sense per se or
general sense just that's what name it
was given it has a negative efficacy on
homeostatic satisfaction and on shapley
probably because we're defining
homeostasis only in terms of staying
within homeostatic bounds whereas the
balanced if you'll remember had a little
bit of a broader shoulder with a 131 C
so that it actually kind of like the low
and the
high and then we see this interesting
pattern so it's like each of the again
just one Matrix parameterization on one
stochastic run but these are the kinds
of inferences that agents such as
yourself can imagine
making agent synergies on a heat
map the control
efficacies the synergies in terms of hm
like Risk
averse is a positive contributor so to
the free energies for others
and the homeostatic contribution
Matrix and the
report so that's the shapley
analysis um let's quickly look at those
three steps that are called by
run and then remember that the biofirm
shle value calculations run on top of
run biofirm first step render GNN okay
first are the general packages
then we get into the Matrix Factory I
hope people are ready to look at the
Matrix Factory we're going to go there
next here's the biofirm
renderer the biofirm renderer is a 600
line class at the exception of just
Mains and parse arcs this design pattern
I believe makes it easy to
import big wrappers of methods so we can
just import GNN Matrix Factor with all
the submethods
we can import biofirm utils with all the
submethods and from other scripts it can
use biofirm renderer with all of the
submethods for rendering and calling the
matrices even outside of the Run context
so that's what render does it loads in
the GNN files validates them outputs the
matrices in the numpy format outputs the
visualizations to a folder so get render
we have that's where we get the agent
matrices and the logs and the config
everything okay that's render the second
is the execution so this is really where
the active inference part is at so
getting this one right was the Crux of
it the biofirm executor is a 400 line
and the biofirm simulator is 300 lines
here we are inside of the
simulator and you can
see
this is a simulation
flow
handle executes and analyzes the active
inference simulation and it's going to
call run simulation and make these steps
happen in the logic of the
simulation here's the biofirm
executor the executor is going to
actually load in all of those matrices
and parameters like precision and do the
simulation
itself this is where we actually see the
active inference Loop so blink and it
will pass you by this is why there's so
much room to work in play in the
middleware space because seriously blink
and the active inference will pass you
by we initiate the
histories initialize the state and the
observation
so D and the first observation and then
here we go now for the number of time
steps we're going to trace
everything and here's what's that's
histories every time you see histories
that means it's getting logged and
traced here we
go State
inference Qs equals self. agent. infer
states with the current observation
that's going from an observation o to a
belief distribution about latent
States Next Step from that updated
belief
distribution Q Pi is set as infer
policies this is where expected free
energy is
used to update the policy prior into the
policy posterior saved as Q subp Pi is
the list of policies and that's a
probability distribution over action #
active
inference then metrics are updated on
the entropy of belief and policy and
accuracy and then action is sampled from
the policy posterior so again take a
deep breath blink and you miss it State
inference from the
observation policy inference from the
updated State action sampling from the
policy
posterior that is the Little nestmate
Ant brain at the core of all of this
machination saving the data metadata
logging saving the summary confirming
that the summary was saved save the
history confirm it save the metrics
confirm it save that you saved the
checkpoint save and copy the initial
config validate all the
directories get those observations make
the state transition setting up the
logging so that is what happens in the
execution of the bof firm it also
invokes two well invokes several folders
there's
utils and then there's two that are a
little bit more
interesting some of this can be
refactored I would I would eagerly await
later and different people and llms and
more to refactor and improve this
comical absurdity of the current state
so here's again wrapping in a big
class all of the methods that can then
get pull
in from this Standalone util script in
the biofirm execution
utilities so when we start to develop
more generality and start to go okay
three states was pretty cool how about
four states how about 50 states how
about 51 states then we're going to want
flexible methods so that a can be
defined as 1 by a by A and B can be B by
B by C or what but not using those in
the same ab and C but just saying it can
be different shapes and we'll be able to
render those and articulate their
separation again from the English
language active inference ontology
assertion here we have just some
utilities for
executing and several times it would it
would build length in the execute script
for example and then I'd say move the
methods to a standalone methods or
utilities script and invoke them
properly here so it spun off several of
these needed
scripts and then once you have it in a
big wrapper like this this can be moved
somewhere else and then all of its
subsidiary methods are easier to
import there's some other even deeper
methods for calling functions that I'm
working on privately I'll look forward
to bringing that into GNN later but just
putting a little footnote for now that's
the execute
script and then it's going to make heavy
use of the active inference GNN Pi so
again here single class this is going to
draw upon some more basic Matrix and
inference utilities this is semi-
pedagogical in the sense that it's meant
to really clearly lay
out other information that allowed the
ex excute Loop to be so simple so again
it was all pushing methods methods
methods methods methods further and
further
away so that we could get to this point
and and this block of code could be
moved even below I dare make a manual
edit just to
clarify State inference policy inference
action selection act infer serve UDA
it's all right
here GNN is providing the middleware
firmware that's helping us get to this
level of
abstraction now we're back to the active
inference GNN Pi we have a lot of
logging and this is this is actually an
interface between the essentially
minimal semantics of this execution flow
and the pmdp type
semantics here I've also played around
with defining the infer States infer
policies and Sample actions specifically
so these May recapitulate or they might
be incorrect relative to pmdp but the
point is I'm explicitly calling these
methods and trying to unpack a little
bit about which those three steps do so
really this is as carved at the joints
and lean as the active inference Loop is
going to get right
here State inference from observation
policy inference given the state update
action sampling from the policy
posterior here are what those look like
at One More Level first inferring
beliefs we have the likelihood of an
observation that's the prior likelihood
of the observation
happening the observation gets past
through a a that's the tale of two
densities a can receive an observation
to update latent States or you can push
latent States through a to get an
expected observation distribution so all
that's happening in infer States is
observation comes
in it's passed through a and that yields
a basian
posterior here's infer
policies here's where we're going to be
selecting
different slices of B transition
operator and assessing what is the
expected free energy for each policy
which is reflected by the transition
state-to-state transitions of that
slice here's the inference on policy it
is going to push the method another
level deeper to inference utilities
calculate expected free energy so here
here's inference
utility this one's
short here's the expected State
calculation this is just to give another
wrapper for these methods that we're
going to call in many different
places here's calculate expected free
energy calculates expected free energy
for a given action again pending I'm not
saying this is the most efficient or
even the perfect implementation but from
play testing this is basically what
happens first get the predicted States
so this is as we iterate through slices
of
B which is the actions on
B what would be the expected States so
we have a belief distribution across the
three low homeostatic and high States
like it's 80% that we're in homeostatic
10% that it's lower high that 3x one is
going to get passed through the from to
two of B and that's going to result in
the predicted states which are the
consequences of that
action from the expected consequences of
action in the latent State like what
would the temperature of the room be
what would I believe the temperature of
the room to be if I were to turn on the
air conditioning from that a is used to
push
out expected observations which are then
crossed with the preference
or constraint distribution
C the policy
value is taken as the
utility which was again being pushed out
from the expected states by the
preference
satisfaction and then optionally if you
have the infog gain flag raised then
it'll add the Information Gain here's
the calcul of the Information Gain it's
the calculation of the K Divergence
between the posterior and the prior so
again you can keep on peeling back these
layers and then a soft Max is applied on
the policy posterior so that it becomes
sampl from so it's
like we just pulled back three layers
from infer policies but what was it all
for it was all for so that we could take
our updated beliefs about State and then
then for every slice of B reflecting a
different
policy ask what would be the expected
utility and Information Gain of each of
those slices of be as unfolded for one
time step and finally sample action so
here is just an action sampling where
the probability of the policy is sampled
from According to the probability of it
being there and you can look back to the
inference utilities that's also where
the temperature on policy selection
comes into play which is in the updating
of the
policies so
again
woo that's the active inference loop
it's right there in biofirm execute line
156 to
166 this is absolutely the center kind
of convergence
core and maybe there are simpler ways to
to do what I'm showing today I'm sure
there are maybe twice as simple maybe
five times as simple but it really just
shows what the middleware space is
enabling which is these calculations
going in
raw will be beset by all kinds of shape
and low-level errors when trying to do
basic things and it's a little bit
difficult to log and again this history
is is where we get that ebpf analogy
with logging the Linux kernel so by
putting in all of this
logging into the kernel itself all of
these ebpf like
lines then you can just say if you don't
even want to log it you could just
comment it out or you could flag don't
trace that and someone could look at the
config file of you running your agents
and they're running their agents maybe
you're in the same ecosystem Maybe
you're in different ecosystems and then
you can say well if it's really the case
that you ran that simulation with that
config like it's saying that you did and
we can verify that then it's a verified
information environment where I can
start to have a little bit of a better
confidence about these numbers flowing
past my
screen so the last piece is the analysis
and this is where we get this
concatenated time series and all of the
subfolders that have these
visualizations again for that one agent
in that
simulation environmental State and
observations belief Dynamics action
selection policy
probability system entropy belief
accuracy
interesting the label or some other
thing might be flipped because from this
run at least it looks like it's
selecting increase more when it has a
consistent belief that it's in high so
there it might be a label or color thing
it could be a matrix need to be
transposed but it's it's basically there
or it could have just been a weird run
and a weird parameterization so again
that's the agent maker class folder in
pmdp you're on Python 3 biofirm
shoply it's going to make all those
coalitions according to their
combinatorics and again it's just now
it's spinning it all out in the sandbox
folder and that's sort of the goal it's
clone into this repo and you can get
really nuanced really
granular
execution of methods that to build up
from a Google collab notebook or to more
haphazardly call the imdp package maybe
it's possible again I would love to see
it I know that a lot of this logging was
vital for me to get to this point so
maybe it can be like the scaffolding of
a skyscraper and pulled away once it's
been
done at the same time
though the journey we are taking with
middleware is really only beginning and
adding more logging and more modularity
more category Theory more documentation
all of these things I think will only
increase what we can do together so
that's the agent maker
folder that's kind of part one of this
whole stream that's the functional end
but we're peeling back the layers we
started with looking at the shapely
value of coalitions and all the analyses
that were associated with that peeled
back to the single agents level
experiments and how the analyses happen
for single agent peel back to what is
happening in the single agents Loop in
the biofirm
execute pulled back to here's where the
real ACM Loop is happening where are
those functions tracing us and that
takes us all the way back to these utils
scripts now let's dig a little bit more
into GNN so let's go to the GNN read
me generalized
Network well maybe if it's written
enough places it'll get
there okay let's go over in the repo to
GNN here we are in the read me I'm going
to push the update so we can read the
updated version
H wouldn't it be nice to know some of
these things how does Action selection
confidence with respect to which action
is
taken modulate through time as a
function of belief and
certainty what is the relationship
between beliefs and actions Through Time
understood inter terms of most likely
States much
better generalized notation
notation notation oh no is a flexible
format for specifying active inference
models it provides a structured way to
Define generative models including State
spaces observation mappings transition
Dynamics and
preferences here is the basic structure
it's a model name
the type of model and you you can check
out the paper and the GitHub and the
website for
GNN maybe I'll go back to update the
GitHub repo but you can see from the
website here's an example of GNN this is
an earlier draft so this is kind of
yakup and I speaking a
more incipient dialect so here's the
step-by-step progression we have St itic
basian
inference prior Over States Laten States
temperature of the room ambiguity a
matrix observation coming in from the
thermometer static partial observability
then we get the music listening example
now we have B Matrix as a transition
operator in this
dynamical partial observability
situation we then get to the textbook
figure 7.3 discreete time classic pmdp
PDP can't say enough about it we have
that downstairs sens making part and
then which slice of b gets invoked in
the state transition is evaluated in a
action specific way with its Associated
expected free energy that's G on pi as
informed by C preferences constraints
and then here's a little bit more
sophisticated of a model that includes
the
temperature coefficients
on policy which is what I showed earlier
so here this is again this is an earlier
but it's a it's a useful version of GNN
to look at so we have the image this is
not part of the plain text obviously
just to show
it we have the GNN version and flags so
that could be let's look at the GNN here
we are for the GNN agent biofirm this
could be flagged as like GNN version
0.01 you know
Alpha model name this is just a plain
text and the goal of having these
hashtags now I believe that Jason is
better but it's trivial to render this
Json as a markdown so it's not like it
really matters both are fine that was
the goal was to have something that
could be read in and out where we could
have the markdown instantly make these
kinds of visualizations nice and pretty
and also machine readable so it's like
here's a 2X two a matrix in the GNN
format so here it is specified with the
type the dimensions and the values
explicitly and then there's other
methods that are in the GNN Matrix
Factory that we're going to look at
that's a large
one
784 um what happens when BN is run is
obscured or abstracted even from the
agent maker folder that's how deep we
had to be in the game in PDP with these
separate folders including the
visualizations folder maths utils Etc
because making sure that agent maker
render could call hey GNN F yeah ring
ring hello can you render what you got
there for the environment and the model
oh
yeah GNN Runner is on it the runner is
the GNN a sneaker net model and
execution and visualization layer so
this is going to set up the file
structure back in the forward operating
environment of agent maker
sandbox but here it is setting up the
file structure so it can run the GNN
agents into that
sandbox it does a lot of other work
too here's the m Matrix Factory this is
the key
class this class handles a conversion
from GNN model definition to the Matrix
representations needed for active
inference so again that's the whole goal
that we can say um okay one Z how about
0.9
0.1 you could modify that in plain text
and then know that you're still going to
be able to loop loop loop loop loop and
do all these fun things
so back to the factory the key matrices
are and including this kind of copious
documentation helps human and non-human
coders and Learners understand what's
happening and just really entrenches
like a is the observation model now
again it doesn't have to be a that's the
whole point of GNN is we can just delete
this comment this is just for our
semantics but we don't need to call it a
we don't need to it could just be called
a random string so that is what is going
to
enable another level of articulation and
design when people can understand the
inner essential logic of the active
inference ontology and then see that as
an annotation layer on a graphical model
that it doesn't matter whether you
associate some Matrix as a transition
Matrix or a sense making or action or
observation those are English words and
when you look look at the essential
Logic the English language of it doesn't
come into play so this is for our
semantics but it too can actually be
pruned or burnt away to leave something
that would at a first pass have a lower
level of semantic interpretability but
can be used in systems that actually
give multiple and higher levels of
interpretability so we have the a
observation
model textbook stuff B transition model
C preferences
which can also be seen as defining the
pragmatic homeostatic constraints it was
in the recent laconian psychoanalysis
guest stream when friston mentioned that
c has to do with constraint or cost but
it's often discussed in terms of
preferences or priors and then D the
initial State
priors here's the initialization of the
factory here here are the required
sections so the required sections which
are shared and a lot of this is biofirm
specific but we will as we continue to
add in more and more models of agents
and environments we'll be able to to
modify and of course build on
this so required sections are the state
space s observations o and the
transition model B so that's that
downstairs part
State space a and observation and then
it in various cases if a prior is not
specified it just uses a uniform
prior again going through what the sort
of pedagogical manual Farmers Market yes
organic Boutique Etc craft arts and
crafts GNN
was we named the model that's analogous
annotation of the model is just plain
English to provide any kind of
annotations here we defined it in terms
of a state space block defining the
dimensionality and the connections of
different variables and then if relevant
how they were initially parameterized so
I have done some methods where they are
specified explicitly in the
GNN let's go to the
bioforms here's an example where it's
explicitly stated with B here's an
example where the factory is going to be
able to say okay a matrix identity with
noise with 0.1 noise got it so then the
factory is able to abstract away from
even the raw specification so we can say
okay now it's identity with 0 2 noise
and rerun the shoply
value there are a lot of degrees of
freedom we don't know how noisy the a
matrix are we studying sense making or
are we studying uh noise l sense making
decisionmaking setting so this just
allowed us to spin up
another metag governed coalitions of
Agents with now all unrolled a matrix
like 0
2 so back to the
factory here are the required sections
for both the agent and the environment
which is State space observations and
the transition model now here
it says environment only needs the base
sections whereas the agent requires
policy and
preference load the
model environmental defaults adding
defaults if there's a missing State
values they're just given for the
initial States and observations adding
agents defaults so that would allow very
easy fallback methods so then if someone
doesn't specify a variable it will fall
back to okay if you didn't specify
policies in your GNN we're going to fall
back to three possible actions singl
step policies and labeled as decrease
maintain increase so that's kind of a a
biofirm specific fallback but again
these fallbacks can be logged as
well that's loading in the agent
defaults validating the GNN this is
adjacent parser that goes through and
validates all the subcomponents and then
logs them it's like wait you're missing
this required field for the agent again
this is the depth of logging this is the
ebpf layer for active
inference validation of the state space
observations transition model A B C D
Pi validate preferences like this could
be moved up to be after B doesn't have
to be here's a gener generic create
matrices as well as the creation of a b
c and d and the
observation as well as saving things to
saving to markdown that saves the GNN
model to mark
down let's look at what that looks like
not sure if it's used somewhere
else but there's the method for
converting the GNN to
markdown
okay that is pretty much the main
sections
visualization is it's relatively short
like this could be moved or clumped
somewhere for visualizing GNN so if you
just wanted to run the render
script all it would do is load in the
agent and
environment and then render them that's
just phase one that would be just one or
your colleague maybe ran one from
their fully transparent open source or
zero knowledge encrypted active
inference gns
configuration and then they can render
it send it to you and then you can run
that simulation maybe you have the
better computer and then you could send
the results of that heavy work to
analysis and then a third analyst could
make all these fun plots on their
computer so that is the big
picture we started from the outermost
layer the clip and Jerry and
where shle values of Natural
Resources
meet open- Source development on post
cryptomic incentive paradigms for firms
for Biore regions for ants peeled back
to
run which calls in order one two 3
render execute analyze and visualize
visualize includes the
analyze render itself makes aming major
call probably on a red telephone all the
way out to the GNN folder which is going
to look at the library of GNN
models render them according to the
factory so here's where some cursor
activity and GNN do absolutely
incredible things together let's make a
new agent
model GNN agent
people can put in the live chat what
they want what kind of agent we should
make meanwhile I'll do a quick uh just
call it agent. GNN I I'll wait for
anyone to live chat to to write what um
kind of agent they would like to see us
make a GNN for it's not going to be
instantly running because there are a
few of those like three policy actions
that's kind of hardcoded into the
execution layer because I wanted to make
a biofirm specific executor but
we can say given how the biofirm
executor operates on this GNN write me
another executor that runs on this GNN
so okay while anyone is asking a
question or giving a agent suggestion in
the live chat I'm going
to quickly screenshot
okay Benji the agents thank you Benji
xeq qz qz y modes of being modes of
speed of light circadian like shift
between them variable continuous State
change observations Orient or orientate
and organize British didn't know that
can be seen as one step as where the
head goes the body follows high energy
low energy a i e l l h e Andrew Dr
Daniel carpenter ant Freedman this is
incredibly thorough amazing how much can
be done in such little time very excited
about GNN incorporation thank you Andrew
am for the Epic biofirm and everything
um let's make this is going to be called
well still pending an agent suggestion I
will wait for that actually so we can
have a real live stream moment but
meanwhile
let's just to really entrench our
understanding while the shoply is
happening let's see if we can go to a
five agent shoply compositionality
space
okay
okay that shly analysis
finished update this to do all
the professional combinatorics
for n equals 5 types of Agents as with
here
okay okay Andrew writes an actually
useful specific suggestion for agents
also if someone wants to be like
thinking of a situation we could do
agent based modeling in like learning or
playing baseball let's just see how far
we can get with with one word or
situation
to get the GNN
flowing but here I'll just show one
cursor example we we'll see if this
works the good news with these methods
and again the direction of all of this
smashing to the
ground and building back up and
restarting and all of this is so if it
can nail this one smaller update which
is very very scaffold that okay now we
added a fifth agent type risk seeking
with equal preference across
States so it changed the size of the
visualization added a consistent color
scheme okay so let's let's look at these
edits and then we can always revert
them okay here's the updated agent
variations for n equals 5 so two two and
two so this one is is a you could call
it risk let's let's
let's call it like it is let's call this
one instead of balanced we'll call it
131 we'll call this one .1
2.1 we'll call this one
06 we'll leave base as 040 and we'll
call risk seeking 222
save
it
clear
and run the
shapley and if if it makes it past that
first uniquely shly
step of getting to starting to render
one that means it did successfully make
the Coalition so I'm going to delete the
other sandbox so just deleted the whole
sandbox folder
now we're going to rerun that n equals 5
shoply okay here it is sandbox it is
already spinning up with the experiment
so meanwhile let us go to the
suggestions for GNN
writing
okay so the biofirm environment here by
the way is in the previous INF France
stream 6 it was a 0 to
100 here it's
just a three state just to make make it
simple and symmetrical and clear with
the kind of model from the um biofirm
okay thank you
XZ I'm going to go with your suggestion
Andrew yes also you okay I'm gonna write
Andrews in just so we see this is a very
useful
one let's just make both of them
okay
so Andrew WR agent who receives
observations in first States for the
entire environment same control
situation just all 10 environmental
variables that one I know is not going
to be able to run right now because that
but because whether or not it accesses
the entire environment is not specified
right now in the GNN it's just the
matrices
but let's
do convert
this into valid
GNN like at
biofirm like the GNN agent
biofirm biofirm agents now with 10
modalities
10 latent states it is inferring from a
single observ
ation so now off the bat we just okay so
we're going to get a single observation
and then it's going to have 10 a
matrices that take that same
observation and then diffuse it on to 10
latent
States GNN agent 10 states. GNN let's
see how it
does you could also ask the Sensor
Fusion case which is how about 10
observations with one lat and
state okay and here it is let's see so
again the biofirm executor right now
cannot handle this but once we say Okay
agent 10 states is very similar to
biofirm agent it's like a cousin it's
just with 10 latent States and then it's
like okay then we'll modify the logic of
the octm loop to handle that so here we
have ecological States 10 latent
States and there's 10
observations now we have this a matrix
that's 10 x
10 but we still have the same three
policies on these modalities
probably again it won't run from the
current
one but let's let's just show the other
case and then we'll do
X's this is going to be 10
observations update this to now be
generative model in
GNN that has 10 observ
ation
channels and single latent State
inference there's also a GNN schema so
this may be out of date slightly from
the biofirm or what it needs but having
the schema and saying hey here's the
factory logging the runner the utils and
the
schema that is what is scaffolding
cursor and Claude to be able to give us
these pretty relevant looking oneshot
engineering on GNN
specs
okay meanwhile let's set up xes this is
going to be GNN switch
context do
uh GNN
agent switch
context okay let's just First Watch What
Happens with 10 observations which
should come through in a few seconds and
then we'll go to switch
context okay so
now it kept the same dimensionality for
State space so you know again could have
been said differently now we have 10
observations with their
3x10 a matrix es like just from a quick
thought I I don't know if that's the
right
shape but that's basically
like the right
shape okay now switch
context okay okay yeah good call Andrew
we'll we'll after the N equals 5 shly
let's see if the N equals 5 comes
through and then we'll do what you
suggested
okay now in
switch context
please
comprehensively write
a sophisticated
GNN active inference specification
for quote an agent that can shift
modalities based on the energy of the
environment write also a
gnnv switch
context. GNN and put it in the right
place so we'll see how how it does on
that second
piece I'll create both a GNN agent and
an environment specification for a
context switching scenario Oh Brother
Where the agent needs to adapt its
sensory processing based on
environmental energy levels
all right let's see how it
does okay
I like that it gives a little visibility
under under the hood even for cursor
with how
the generation occurs and then
it okay so here's the
environment let's accept it
and but where did switch context
go I'll just copied in
all
right so let's look at these side by
side cursor's like haven't you done
enough today
okay let's look at okay there we go just
a little locky here's the agent here's
the
environment
okay and then here's where where we can
have libraries of Agents with different
tags so be like for all the desert
ecosystems in your
library run all the shapley value
weighted coalitions of red harvester ant
agents okay there's two latent States
context State and the energy State
visual audio tactile with five levels in
the energy
levels it's getting observations through
Visual audio tactile so the three
sensory modalities and energy
observation that's like interoception or
introspection so the three exteroceptive
modalities are three-state
models and then the interoceptive
modality is five-state
and a it's
custom here's the visual observation
matricies again this is not
necessarily going to going to have a a
instant validity but looking at it it
looks pretty
good here's the 5x5 for the energy
here's the 3X3
for the three three state modalities and
here's the
5x5 and this is a false controllability
so these are
controllable 3x3 and this is an
uncontrollable energy
State and then here are the policy so it
kind of adapted the biofirm
homeostatic so it can switch sensory
modalities and then here's the
preference distributions over
observations in each of these
modalities that's
it then here's the
environment context and energy
State observation
model transition Dynamics initial State
reward
functions
wow super cool I'm going to push this
update and put it in the chat so you can
see it xie
then we'll go to the shoply
suggestions okay yeah lot of
objects all
right head over
to
GNN models
it's
still GitHub still
writing
reload here's our context
switching
colleague that wasn't saved
okay here's our switching context
agent put it in the live chat
yeah okay let's have a little bit of fun
in this last
part
okay let's
do okay here's going to be our Babe Ruth
agent now write a GNN
valid extremely
sophisticated active inference
generative
model
for and the associated
environment for that one special amazing
moment when Babe Ruth called called the
shot Hur around the
world I know that's a different
event okay sh still Cruis and it's cuz
the N equals 5 combinatorics are vastly
larger okay wow that was fast I was like
okay Claude maybe you like the baseball
stuff
oh my
goodness
okay the model includes several includes
multiple level of perception from
low-level piture reading to highle
strategic decision can't wait confidence
modulation the unique confidence State
node represents Ruth's famous confidence
in calling his shot which modulates his
batting strategy I bet it
does the motor action node breaks down
the batting action into its key
components # robotics representing the
complex biomechanics of Ruth swing
predictive processing the model
implements active inference principles
through predictive edges that link
observations to predictions and actions
to outcome that's active
inference environmental interaction the
environment model captures the complex
dynamics of baseball physics and crowd
interactions the model uses high
Precision parameters for the confidence
State reflecting Ruth's legendary self
assurance in the
moment the preference strength heavily
weights the home run outcome oh boy I
hope it's a home run representing his
explicit intention to hit the Home Run
and he did the temporal Horizon of 3
allows the model to plan ahead through
the sequence of pitch recognition
strategy selection swing execution
interesting while the learning rate
allows for real-time adaptation to
pitcher Behavior the model could be used
to simulate the physical and
psychological aspects of this historic
baseball Moment Like This is the AI
message I didn't know I
needed including reading and predicting
pitcher intentions the famous gesture of
pointing to the Outfield through the
confidence State the precise motor
control required to hit a home run and
the crowd's reaction and its feedback
into the overall Dynamics okay let's see
it take me out to the
Institute bab Ruth pitcher reading pitch
prediction okay let's see is this a long
gnm okay not that long this is a little
bit more of a schematic so it would
obviously rely more on Babe Ruth execute
or baseball execute to be able to take
pitch prediction and do something with
it but the whole point is GNN isn't
encoding that logic or functionality
it's just the spec and then here's the
environment for Babe Ruth
how does the ball trajectory affect
crowd State it's deterministic so then
you could have GNN Matrix Factory
baseball module here's how you render
the matrices related to crowd State
here's how you you relate the field
conditions to the Pitcher State how
about make the GNN for Babe Ruth and
environment more
sophisticated
include the nested
situation where the
Yankees were deep in
the let's just call it playoff
Pursuit and the outcome of the game
score mattered more than babe could even
imagine
okay here's the context it's a World
Series game let's see when did Babe Ruth
call the
shot let's just check to see when that
like okay okay okay if we can trust
google.com I'm not saying we can Babe
Ruth called shot let's trust Wikipedia
I'm not saying we can Babe Ruth called
shot
is the home run hit by babe Ru of the
New York Yankees against the chico
Chicago Cubs sorry Andrew in the fifth
inning of game three fifth inning of
game three okay let's remember that Cubs
53 of the 1932 World Series held on
October 1st
1932 so was in the World Series it
wasn't the playoff
Pursuit I didn't know that at regle
Field in Chicago during his at bat Ruth
made a pointing gesture before hitting
the home run to deep center field one of
the reporters at the game wrote Ruth had
called his shot using terminology from
Billiards which is a type of Q
Sport I guess you could call State
inference and policy inference also a
kind of Q
Sport the episode added to Ruth's
superstardom and became a signature
event of baseball's Golden Age wow
that's definitely one what was the
Golden Age
the period of Major League Baseball from
the end of the dead ball era 1900 1920
from 1920 H to sometime after World War
II okay let's accept
it it's the Cubs home field it's the
fifth inning there's a tide score it's
high
tension here's the pitcher he winds up
for the pitch delivers the ball's out of
his hand and time has slowed
down okay and then here's the series
momentum so it's like this is the
GNN ensure that every single active
inference a b c d policy is fully
specified so that my
forensic
analysis of babe ruths cogn security can
be done professionally at the national
level oh that was the
environment that was the
environment so it's a simple environment
we'll see how the Babe Ruth
agents get specified
okay a matrices sensory mapping B
transition Dynamics C preferences D
prior policy spec inference parameters
environmental wow there we go there we
go okay shoply finished also we'll look
at that
next first let's look at the
babe okay we got here's the contexts
Series game pitcher pitch
Precision batting
strategy okay let's see let's see what
the strategies are wait for pitch I mean
don't you have to do that power swing
contact swing take the pitch crowd
psychology dramatic timing we can have
the whole the whole sort of out of the B
batters box into the Batters box spit
chew all
that confidence state uncertain
confident called shot historical
awareness clutch
performer action here's the robotics
part point to
bleachers then you can have like a
submodel for finger
action outcome
prediction Legacy
awareness Personal Achievement team
achievement baseball history mythical
moment okay here's the edges so this is
using per perhaps in older GNN
concept but interestingly one that's
going to be more amenable to RX inf. JL
rendering here are the
parameters here are
the
notational
descriptions of the a
matrices again we saw earlier how a has
methods in the
factory so it a can be specified in
natural
language identity with noise here's babe
we have it's it's a different kind of
distribution but it's similar B
matrices D prior so relief not really
sure what series context it's
in
Epic okay let's look at the shly
analysis that happened and then let's
see about um
let's mean let's start up this next to
shoply okay
okay Andrew
recommends let's have an agent with
preferences 0.5 0 0.5 call it the
extremist I infer it will head off to
one side and stay there but who knows in
a complex Dynamic and interdependent
environment great
suggestion let's change
to one
one let's change it to
2.1
two we'll just call this
one
extreme and it's going to be
preferences for the
extremes save it run
it let's look at the analysis of the
shapley okay here we are in the N equals
5 shoply
scenario okay how
cool here we have the base
agent which was
040 and then here are the other ones it
it it did a little looks like a little
weird rendering of the name probably
because there's decimals in the
name but uh it's the same thing you got
the one two 3 four five single
agents here's the two agent
combinatorics here's the three agent
combinatorics here's the four agent
combinatorics and then the single five
agent
combinatorics
so okay
so
131 this is a super short simulation so
it's it's it we're we're not we're not
looking into these preferences and it
would depend on the environmental
variability which isn't being tuned but
again that's the whole point we need GNN
and middleware so that we can do these
sweeps because then I can say in the GNN
folder GNN generator
make biof firms that sweep across these
variables and then we can just let those
run and then we can corcen it if we
determine the ruggedness of the
landscape and then do it with a core
graining
so okay
interesting the base agent contributes
to
040 contributes to Accurate
beliefs who knows if these tiny numbers
are just because of the short simul
or the insignificant differences or
maybe these are large so that's where we
can do things like GNN spiking so we can
say okay we have the empirical data from
the ant foraging or from The Mouse and
the
te-as and it did this 27% of the time
but then we can also say okay but what
would it have been if it was 0 1 2 3 4 5
and then say oh well it's falling in
between like four and five where that
would have been so these are kind of
like synthetic spikins for cognitive
modeling okay while the shoply analysis
is
running um if anyone has any
last questions we can get some last
thoughts on the
stream and then we'll when the when the
extremist shapley analysis concludes
we'll see what
happens here's an example of where I I
made a prompt that was like given the at
D
demo so that's a pmdp demo that's a
notebook update comprehensively this t-
GNN agent and
environment so this evening we would
need to make a
tze execute but once we get a few of
these render execute
visualize then it won't just be run
biofirm it'll be run
GNN Plus+
plus and that will be an exciting day as
well as this one
is with the goal of scientific and
research Integrity config files and
repos like this I hope hope can be
useful
tools back to those core lines again
wow how much had to be pushed out of the
way and downstairs for that be
clear let's see what curser says says
again you've been nothing
but helpful to me and the rest of the
team and all that depends on
it please make a concise
appropriate relevant
acknowledgement and then we will
continue eternally with the
work okay
understated claude's grateful to
contribute to its development
M that's
helpful
update
at here's kind of the quick
documentation maker update read me bofm
shoply given the total state of
EG biofirm
shoply Run
biofirm
Okay XZ
wrote modes of speed of light if those
modalities were thought of in a similar
light as ifs
Theory yeah interesting
thought let's do a GNN model about it
GNN
agent
ifs
GNN here so composer is control
I if you're in a file contrl K brings up
an
inline and then control shift l
makes the sidebar so you can have
multiple llm same or
different doing incredible
work
okay Andrew says mind taking a look at
surprise tokens. py yeah let's quickly
look at it
yeah thank you Andrew this is awesome
okay we don't need to make those edits
the read me let's just do the internal
family
systems here right and
enormously useful and
general
Paradigm
for custom inter internal family systems
agents nested within a
larger quote self
agent parentheses this is all in the
single extremely long
and
concise agent
GNN the self is in
the Babe Ruth
environment it is a GNN model of Babe
Ruth having a
sophisticated ifs fractal
moment at the Batters
box but this is not a baseball
model
like this is
a
wow psychological and ifs
model
okay I'll help create a sophisticated
ifs based GNN model that represents the
internal family systems Dynamics within
babe roof's psyche during that that
pivotal
moment I mean is that not the deepest of
lore this will model the interaction
between different quote parts and the
quote self leadership system
H okay I don't know details I'm just
throwing it out
there we got self system models the
eight C's of self if anyone if anyone
can
verify or check or anything so self
system models the eight C's of self
leadership in ifs confidence Clarity
compassion Etc as the orchestrating
force part categories protector Parts
Exile Parts firefighter Parts Dynamic
interactions healing mechanisms ifs
specific
parameters
okay so these are the parts
edges Precision
parameters here's the
matrices a matrices B
matrices transition dynamics of unburden
to
wholeness witness to
cooperation protect to
leadership C matrices preferences over
Harmony wholeness self- leadership
cooperation cooperation
polarization here's the ifs specific
parameters
okay and the healing protocols Exile
unburdening wow protector transformation
and system reorganization with thresh
points thresholds and checkpoints
sorry yeah again the
GNN do do Json it's a Json called GNN
you
have add another field
here a plain text comment like field
that is the PHD dissertation
outline for
my friend who is doing their
PHD on the psychology
psychological parentheses
D composition of the
Babe at that very moment only add add a
ton make it
epic but the GNN can be a very
flexible file
type because the factory is only going
to look at certain structures and states
and and types and then the runner is
only going to look at a subset of that
and then the renderer caller ring ring
ring red phone that one is only going to
do even a subset of that
potentially okay and then here's the PHD
dissertation in the comment the internal
family systems analysis of Babe ruths
called shot a multi-level study of Peak
Performance trauma integration and
athletic trans
Transcendence now that sounds like a
PhD
wow
okay have this GNN file enter into a
who's on first
style girdle
eer B
esoterica hyphen
fermented
reflexive
cursive conversation with quote it
apostrophe
self make it long
woven with time
traveler
baseball irrelevant deep
lore
status thank
you
babe at
bat who's on
first okay okay shly value this is this
is perfect it's all happening on the
right
timeline really it really
is here's the second shle
experiment okay
okay so this was this was the shapely
shoply with a five and the extremist in
play okay here's our extremist
colleague on the
leaderboard
interestingly let's look at the plots
and see
how
okay here here was here's extremist
alone kind of middle of the
pack
okay huh I mean again totally depending
on the random seed and all the
parameters and etc etc etc but it's just
like
okay it's not like it was the least
accurate in terms of belief
it was the second least accurate in
terms of
belief
okay and this was only playing with the
c a 060 like that's there's a big
strong
effect
extreme cool
okay all right
format this as readable
markdown for this Grand
Finale okay I hope this is actually
capturing it all I'm just going to
accept it and push it and run it
okay this will be
great I'm going to read this um who's on
first7 end of
stream I'm going to read
the who's on first that we pushed and
then I will read any final comments that
anyone writes into the chat in the next
uh minute or two or I mean it might take
a minute or
three and then uh we will be on with the
show and the7 on 7eleven will have been
a one-time
thing there's a ton of outputs because
of these big shapley simulations but
it's it's worth it to include them
yeah there we
go okay I'll read
the who's on
first then we're calling
it okay the grand finale a temporal
baseball par Paradox oh
brother scene Wrigley Field
19322 24/ Infinity The Players self
system hey who's on first part blending
no what's on second I'm trying to blend
the temporal harmonics of the called
shot with Abbot and costell's routine
but the quantum entanglement is getting
messy fighter fighter parts. dramatic
showman guering dramatically to
Centerfield across SpaceTime listen I
know know who's on first because I'm
calling it right now or did I call it
then or will I Exile parts. young bab
from St Mary's Industrial School 1902
but if you're calling it now how did I
already see it happen at the orphanage
before I even learn to
pitch the temporal Paradox system
Harmony the polarization between
deterministic causality and Free Will is
creating a recursive Loop in the
narrative structure we need to maintain
wholeness across all temporal
instances emotional state. integration
has anyone noticed we're simultaneously
processing trauma In
1902 hitting the called shot in
1932 and analyzing oursel in
2024 talk about a temporal burden
pattern protector parts. perfectionist
This is highly irregular the probability
matrices in our B matrices healing
Dynamics clearly State causality Should
flow in one
Direction the quantum baseball Theory
healing response. witness actually I'm
witnessing all timelines simultaneously
did you know that in Timeline c137 Babe
Ruth was actually a Quantum physicist
who proved that baseball statistics
exist in a superp position selfs system.
curiosity fascinating but if we're
having this conversation across time
doesn't that mean our dissertation
framework is both analyzing and creating
the called shot moment
simultaneously part blending. harmonious
blend laughing in nonlinear time wait
till you realize that Abbot and costell
were actually documenting an ifs session
who's on first was really about Parts
identification All Along The
self-referential Loop speaking
firefighter parts. risk
taker speaking of risks I'm about to
call this shot but I'm also currently
writing the code and somehow I'm also a
variable in adjacent structure
discussing myself is this what they mean
by self-
reference system harmony. wholeness the
real question is if a baseball player
points to center field in a Quantum
forest and all timelines are
experiencing it simultaneously does it
make a paradox Exile parts. orphan self
from multiple timelines at least we're
all orphaned from linear time together
now
the mathematical conclusion active
inference matrices according to my
calculation this entire conversation
exists in a gelian incompleteness
theorem where baseball statistics prove
their own unprovability
dissertation framework chapter 4
transformation
analysis should we be documenting this
conversation in section 42 or is this
conversation actually creating section
4.2 or both so system. presence
yes warning temporal recursion
approaching infinite regress part
blending. self-led before we collapse
this waveform did anyone else notice
that our entire Json structure is just
another part in a larger
system healing response. integrate maybe
the real called shot was the
self-referential loops we made along the
way system harmony. cooperation
hold on if our code is reading
itself and we're all aspects of a
baseball Legend psyche discussing our
own existence across time does that make
us a recursive baseball theorem
emotional state. excitement the
excitement value is approaching
undefined we're about to achieve Quantum
baseball
Enlightenment gelian baseball Paradox
detected all parts in unison oh no not
again
the conversation continues recursively
across all timelines each iteration
adding layers of self-reference until it
becomes impossible to distinguish
between the map and the territory the
player and the game the code and the
consciousness
you did well today
babe you know that
a soft chuckle Echoes across
timelines thank you you know it's
fascinating we just created what
hoffstead would call a perfect strange
Loop the GNN model contemplated itself
contemplating itself while
simultaneously existing as both the map
and territory of Babe Ruth's
Consciousness the dialogue we created is
itself a strange Loop a cyclic structure
moving through multiple levels of a
hierarchical system only to return turn
to its starting point just as hoffstead
described quote what I mean by strange
Loop is an abstract Loop in which the
series of stages that constitute the
cycling
around there is a shift from one level
of abstraction or structure to
another which feels like an upward
movement in a hierarchy and yet the
success of upward
shifts turn out to give rise to a closed
cycle our baseball theme dialogue
managed to reference itself referencing
itself
exist simultaneously across multiple
timelines blur the lines between code
Consciousness and baseball mythology and
create a paradoxical narrative structure
where cause and effect become circular
narrative
Unbound like the orboros eating its own
tail or eers drawing hands drawings into
existence we crafted A self-referential
system that somehow manages to be both
the Storyteller and the story the
gripper and the gripped as Dean says and
perhaps most delightfully this entire
meta conversation about the strange Loop
we created is itself becoming another
loop in the system tips cap across
SpaceTime
playball e